C. Chaillé-Long Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
C. Chaillé-Long Papers 1809-1918 1863-1918
MSS15479
Chaillé-Long, C. (Charles), 1842-1917
1,800 items
3 containers
1.2 linear feet
2 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Soldier, explorer, and diplomat. Personal and official correspondence, articles, speeches, news clippings, scrapbook, awards, commissions, maps, and photographs concerning Chaillé-Long's career as an explorer and public servant.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Ardouin, D. F.--Correspondence.; Baratieri, Oreste--Correspondence.; Beresford, Charles William de la Poer Beresford, Baron, 1846-1919--Correspondence.; Blair, Montgomery, 1813-1883--Correspondence.; Field, Sue Virginia--Correspondence.; Gavillot, J. C. Aristide (Jean Claude Aristide), 1837- --Correspondence.; Giraud, Paul--Correspondence.; Gordon, Charles George, 1833-1885.; Ismail, Khedive of Egypt, 1830-1895--Correspondence.; Jusserand, J. J. (Jean Jules), 1855-1932--Correspondence.; Le Myre de Vilers, Charles Marie, 1833-1918--Correspondence.; Orillat, Paul H.--Correspondence.; Proctor, Edward Dean--Correspondence.; Taillet, Paul--Correspondence.; Vignaud, Henry, 1830-1922--Correspondence.
Subjects
Geography--Africa.; Geography--Korea.
Places
Africa--Discovery and exploration.; Alexandria (Egypt)--History--Bombardment, 1882.; Egypt--History--British occupation, 1882-1936.; Nile River--Discovery and exploration.
Titles
Charles Chaillé-Long papers
Occupations
Diplomats.; Explorers.; Soldiers.
Acquisition Information
The papers of C. Chaillé-Long, soldier, explorer, and diplomat, were given to the Library of Congress by his niece, Lucy Digger Long Swann Sinclair, in 1919.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of C. Chaillé-Long are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of these papers is available on two reels. Consult a reference librarian in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1842, July 2 Born, Princess Anne, Md.
1860 Educated, Washington Academy, Maryland
1861 1865 Civil War service, private to captain
1869 1870 Commissioned lieutenant colonel, Egyptian Army; professor of French, military school, Cairo, Egypt
1871 1873 Served Alexandria infantry, General Staff, Cairo, Egypt
1874 1877 Chief of staff to Charles George Gordon
1874 Executed treaty annexing Uganda to Egypt; documented Lake Ibrahim, Nile Valley; promoted to colonel
1877 Published Central Africa: Naked Truths of Naked People. New York: Harper & Brothers
1880 Graduated, Columbia University Law School, New York, N.Y.
1881 Served international tribunals, Alexandria, Egypt
1882 United States consul, Alexandria, Egypt, during bombardment of the city by the British Mediterranean Fleet; decorated Cross of Commander of the Osmanieh
1883 Practiced international law, Paris, France
1884 Published The Three Prophets. New York: D. Appleton and Co.
1887 1889 United States consul general to Korea; explored Qualelpart Island and Han River
1890 Married Marie Amelie Hammond
1891 Published Les Sources du Nil. Rouen: Impr. de E. Cagniard
1897 1900 Served U.S. special commissions, Paris, France
1901 Decorated, Légion d'Honneur
1908 1916? Editorial staff member, Washington Sunday Star
1917, Mar. 24 Died, buried in Arlington National Cemetery, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
Charles Chaillé-Long (1842-1907) was perhaps best known as a soldier, explorer, and first person from the United States to visit and document Lake Ibrahim in the Nile Valley in 1874, and his papers document his African experiences as well as some of his activities as writer, lecturer, practitioner of international law, and diplomat. The majority of the papers are related to the period in the 1870s and 1880s when Chaillé-Long was in Egypt, although the collection as a whole covers the period from 1863 to 1918, with the exception of two letters from Winfield Scott (1786-1866) to A. Porter in 1809-1910. The Scott letters may have come from the Chaillé-Long family or may have been used by Chaillé-Long in his historical studies.
The collection consists of General Correspondence, Subject File, Speeches and Writings, and Miscellany series, but the papers are limited in both scope and amplitude. Although Chaillé-Long family history is documented in applications to the Society of the Sons of the American Revolution and in biographical articles, there are no other references to Chaillé-Long's childhood or family. There are only a few documents from his service in the Civil War, from his practice in international law, and from his tour as consul general in Korea. Many of the papers relate to his attempt to secure an appointment in the United States Foreign Service, to obtain remuneration from the Egyptian government, or to qualify for an army pension in 1907. Consequently, his activities as an officer in the army of Ismail, Khédive of Egypt (1870-1877) and as temporary United States consul during the bombardment of Alexandria in 1882 by the British are well documented. His writings about his experiences in Africa and in the Far East are incomplete but are well represented in the collection, both in manuscript and printed form.
The collection provides source material for studies in the late nineteenth-century history of the Nile Valley, including personal studies of Charles George Gordon and of the Khédive, as well as comments on Egyptian society and the explorations and explorers of the time. Some source material is also included on China in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. Most of the material reflects Chaillé-Long's personal view of the times, his comments on the diplomatic service, foreign affairs, and the peoples of alien lands from the point of view of one who was outside the State Department's scope of activities.
Papers in the collection are primarily in English, but many are in French, and a few are in Italian, Arabic, Turkish, and Japanese. Turkish documents include Chaillé-Long's military promotion in the Khédive's army and his decorations by Abdul Mejid, Sultan of Turkey. Included also is a Japanese biography of Chaillé-Long that was written at the time of his diplomatic service in Korea.
Scattered throughout the collection are documents relating to awards and memberships, to the French Legion of Honor, presidential appointments from Grover Cleveland, appearances before various geographical and historical societies, the masonic order, law degrees, and qualification and appointment papers.
The General Correspondence series treats social as well as professional issues and affairs, with many letters of testimonial concerning Chaillé-Long's activities in Egypt in the 1880s. A few copies of Chaillé-Long's own letters are included in this series, as well as in other series. Among the significant correspondents in the collection are D. F. Ardouin, Oreste Baratieri, Baron Charles William de la Poer Beresford, Montgomery Blair, Sue Virginia Field, J. C. Aristide Gavillot, Paul Giraud, J. J. Jusserand, Ismail, Khédive of Egypt, Charles Marie le Myre de Vilers, Paul H. Orillat, Edward Dean Proctor, Paul Taillet, and Henry Vignaud.
The Subject File includes correspondence of a routine nature concerning the organizations with which Chaillé-Long was affiliated, certificates of memberships, awards or honors, member activities, and military records. Also in the file is biographical, bibliographical, and genealogical material.
Files in the Speeches and Writings series include Chaillé-Long's annotated writings on Gordon, the Khédive, the Nile Valley people, and impressions of China and Africa. A scrapbook in the Miscellany series contains articles from French and American journals by and about Chaillé-Long mostly relating to Egypt and the Nile Valley.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in four series:
General Correspondence, 1809-1916
Subject File, 1865-1911
Speeches and Writings, 1863-1918
Miscellany, 1876-1918
Container List
Available on microfilm. Shelf no. 16,352
- General Correspondence, 1809-1916 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  Personal and professional correspondence, mostly of letters received, with some copies of letters sent. Includes two letters from Winfield Scott (1786-1866) to A. Porter.
  Arranged in chronological groupings and therein by name of correspondent.
  - 1809-1810 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Scott, Winfield (1786-1866), letters to A. Porter (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 1869 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Blair, Montgomery (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Maury, Dabney H. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Taylor, George C. (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 1874 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Beardsley, R. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Blair, Montgomery (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Ishmaël Khédive of Egypt (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Khaïry (Reel 1)
    - Southworth, Alran [?] (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Trudivaux [?] (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 1879-1884 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Bates, H. W. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Chaix, P. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Fuld, Stephen (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Gianonez [?] (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Giraud, Paul (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Gordon, Charles George (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Hermanos, N. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Hunter, W. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Hutchins, C. (Reel 1)
    - Loring, W. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Nicholson, J. W. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Store, Charles P. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Taillet, Paul (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Voner [?] (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Wallace, Lewis (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 1885-1891 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Blaine, James Gillespie (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Giraud, Paul (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Haardt, Hermann (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Harrison, Burton N. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Hurlbut, George C. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Martin, John Brisban (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Toutain, Paul (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Voission, Louis Pierre (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 1892-1895 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Aide, E. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Ardouin, D. F. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Cambour [?] (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Chaix, P. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Collin du Tann [] (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Fechét, Eugene O. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Gravier, Gabriel (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Hild, S. A. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Kleczkowski, A. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Malvano (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Orillat, Paul H. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Phelps, William Walter (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Taillet, Paul (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Vignaud, Henry (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 1897-1898 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Baratieri, Oreste (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Fuld, Stephen (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Liernur, W. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Porter, John Addison (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 1900-1901 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Ardouin, D. F. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Baratieri, Oreste (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Barber, J. M. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Bataïr [?] (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Field, Sue Virginia (Mrs. Stephen) (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Gauthiot, Charles (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Harrison, Thomas Shelton (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Jones, Georgina (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Le Myre de Vilers, Charles Marie (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Manning, Margaritte (Mrs. Daniel) (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Rigumm [?], Victor (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Taillet, Paul (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Gavillot, J. C. Aristide (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Vignaud, Henry (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - to General Bassot 18 May 1901 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 1903-1904 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Adee, Alvey A. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Goodrich, C. F. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Hall, W. V. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Jusserand, J. J. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Le Myre de Vilers, Charles Marie (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Mitchell, Weir (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Penros, Boies (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Gavillot, J. C. Aristide (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - to Theodore Roosevelt (1858-1919) (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 1906-1911 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Bacon, Robert1 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Barber, J. M. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Beresford, Charles William de la Poer, Baron (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Curtis, A. T. [?] (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Farid, M. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Howe, Mark A. De Wolfe (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Hutchins, C. T. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Jusserand, J. J. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Lee, G. W. Custis (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Le Myre de Vilers, Charles Marie (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Pinchon, S. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Proctor, Edward Dean (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Reid, Whitelaw (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Sherman, William T. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Taft, William H. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Whitehouse, F. Cope (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 1912-1916, undated (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Bates, Oric (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Beresford, Charles William de la Poer, Baron (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Lansing, Robert (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - McClellan, Ellen (undated) (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Proctor, Edward Dean (Box 1, Reel 1)
- Subject File, 1863-1918 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  Correspondence, applications for membership, notices, awards, honors, records, and miscellaneous material relating to organizations and the military.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject and therein chronologically.
  - Biographical, bibliographical, 1893-1915 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Historical societies, 1897-1910 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Geographical societies, 1877-1910 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Institute Egyptien, 1875-1900 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Law, international, 1881-1885 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Légion d'Honneur, 1901 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Military records (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Egypt, 1869-circa 1900 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - United States, 1865-1886, 1904-1907 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Society of the Sons of the American Revolution, 1890-1911 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - State Department, Korea, 1887-1889 (Box 1, Reel 1)
- Speeches and Writings, 1863-1918 (Box 1-2, Reel 1)
  Handwritten and printed speeches and articles, clippings, programs, notes, and fragments.
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Acceptance of Charles P. Daly medal, 1910 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Address on China, 1916 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - "Adieu Chosen," post-1889 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - "Commercial Geography," post-1900 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Dedication G. Washington statue, Paris, France, 1900 (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - "General Gordon, More Soldier than Saint," 1902 (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - "Lam Lam a Bedouin Baby," undated (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - "Modern Arabian Nights," undated (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - "Old Brittany," undated (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - On the flag, post-1900 (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - “Revolution in Russia," 1917 (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - "The Forgotten American Mission to Egypt," 1912 (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - "The Key to the Tragedy of Gordon's Death," post-1885 (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - The Three Prophets: Chinese Gordon, Mohammed-Ahmed, Arabi Pasha (1884) (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - Notes and fragments, circa 1863-1913, undated (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - Printed articles and speeches, circa 1876-1917 (Box 2, Reel 1)
- Miscellany, 1866-1918 (Box 2-3, Reel 1-2)
  Printed matter, awards, photographs, clippings about Chaillé-Long, social engagements, and articles by and about Chaillé-Long in a scrapbook.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Awards and certificates, including military buttons, 1881-1904 (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - Photographs and sketches, circa 1874-1900 (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - Press, publicity about Chaillé-Long, 1876-1918, undated (Box 3, Reel 2)
  - Printed matter, including pictures, maps, and annotations, circa 1882-1914 (Box 3, Reel 2)
  - Scrapbook, including articles and clippings by and about Chaillé-Long, 1866-1905 (Box 3, Reel 2)
  - Social invitations, clubs, and obituaries, 1876-1913 (Box 3, Reel 2)
  - Extra copies, duplicates of correspondence, writings, and other material, 1874-1900 (Box 3, Reel 2)